# Jacob O. Spiegel, Ph.D.

Pittsburgh, PA 

ispiegel@pitt.edu 

(516) 984-7751 in linkedin.com/in/jacob-spiegel-phd/

I am seeking to transition from academia to industry. I am self-motivated and a fast learner, and I love working on team-based collaborations.

With a Ph.D. in molecular biophysics, a Ph.D. minor in teaching, and a Bachelor of Engineering, I have a multi-disciplinary background. I have three years of computational biology, Python programming, and open-source tool-development experience, as well as ten years of wet lab experience. I hope to bring my diverse background in science, engineering, and communications to tackle interdisciplinary challenges.

# Education

## University of Pittsburgh

2014 - 2020

# Ph.D in Molecular Biophysics and Structural Biology

Pittsburgh, PA

- Thesis title: "Targeting the Poly (ADP-Ribose) Polymerase-1 Catalytic Pocket Using AutoGrow4, a Genetic Algorithm for De Novo Design"

#### Ph.D Minor in Teaching

## Carnegie Mellon University

2013 - 2014

Ph.D. Student in Molecular Biophysics and Structural Biology

Pittsburgh, PA

Stony Brook University B.Eng. in Biomedical Engineering - Cellular and Molecular Biology Track

2009 - 2013Stony Brook, NY

# Professional Experience

## University of Pittsburgh

2013 - 2020

# Ph.D. Candidate/Researcher in Dr. Jacob Durrant's laboratory

Pittsburgh, PA

- Designed, developed, documented, and maintained multiple Python open-source programs for computer-aided drug designed (CADD) and cheminformatics; parallelized code for multiprocessing
- Applied CADD techniques to biological targets; performed molecular dynamic (MD) and weighted ensemble MD simulations on multiple proteins; performed protein homology modeling
- Completed independent and collaborative projects
- Authored scientific articles for publication
- Mentored, managed, and designed projects for/with undergraduate and graduate students

#### Ph.D. Candidate in Dr. Roger Hendrix's laboratory

- Studied bacteriophages using biochemical, molecular genetic, and X-ray crystallography techniques
- Engineered plasmids; designed protein purification protocols; purified proteins for X-ray crystallography

## Stony Brook University

2011 - 2013

# Undergraduate Researcher in Dr. Balaji Sitharaman's laboratory - Studied nanoparticle drug delivery system targeting cancer cells

Stony Brook, NY

- Designed alternative exfoliation protocol to produced graphene sheets from graphite

#### **Publications**

#### Peer-Reviewed Articles

- **Spiegel, J.O.**, Durrant, J.D. AutoGrow4: an open-source genetic algorithm for *de novo* drug design and lead optimization. J Cheminform 12, 25 (2020). http://doi.org/ggwwcp
- Ropp, P.J., **Spiegel, J.O.**, et al. Gypsum-DL: an open-source program for preparing small-molecule libraries for structurebased virtual screening. J Cheminform 11, 34 (2019). http://doi.org/gf48dh

#### **Articles in Preparation**

- **Spiegel, J.O.**, O'Donnell, A., Durrant, J.D., (2020). Molecular dynamics of α-arrestin TXNIP.
- Spiegel, J.O., Durrant, J.D., (2020). Mechanism and Pharmaceutical Intervention of Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase 1 (PARP-
- **Spiegel, J.O.**, Durrant, J.D., Bowman, R., O'Donnell, A. (2020). Putting the brakes on α-arrestin trafficking: α-arrestin regulation by phosphorylation and ubiquitination.